<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Algos-ds on Aditya Bhatia Blog!</title>
    <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Algos-ds on Aditya Bhatia Blog!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Aditya Bhatia © 2022</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 12:28:48 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tree Traversal</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/tree-traversal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 12:28:48 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/tree-traversal/</guid>
      <description>Trees can be traversed in multiple ways. This document talks about multiple ways to traverse tree. I added templates for the such traversal here for easy reference and also set of sample problems to practice the templates on.
 Level-wise Tree Traversal  A level-wise traversal of the tree can be described as visiting the nodes in the tree from root to the leaves such that all the parents at the same distance from root are visited before their children.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Binary Search II</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/binary-search-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 11:33:37 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/binary-search-ii/</guid>
      <description>In the previous article related to binary search, when the element is found and when element is not found in a sorted array. In this article will look at binary search when overall array is exactly not sorted.
Example Problem:
 Peak index in a mountain Array  In this problem, a peak is somewhere middle of the array. All the elements to the left and right of the peak are monotonically decreasing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Binary Search I</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/binary-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 14:01:53 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/binary-search/</guid>
      <description>Binary search is the fastest way to search elements in sorted static array have time complexities of O(logn). In this article will look a template for doing binary search and then extending that template for variants of binary search problems.
Example
 Binary Search  Template for Iterative Binary Search
def binarySearch(nums: List[int], target: int) -&amp;gt; int: st, end = 0, len(nums) - 1 while st &amp;lt;= end: mid = st + (end - st)//2 if nums[mid] == target: return mid if nums[mid] &amp;lt; target: st = mid + 1 else: end = mid - 1 return -1  Other Examples:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervals</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/intervals/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 23:37:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/intervals/</guid>
      <description>In this article will talk about the interval problems, and look for pattern in such problems. In interval problems a sequence of overlapping and non-overlapping intervals are given denoted by [start, end] time on the number line.
Example such problems
 Merge Intervals  An interval is defined by a range by two points, start and end both inclusive. An overlap of two intervals can be seen in four ways, if one of the interval is taken as a reference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sliding Window II</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sliding-window-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 22:56:57 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sliding-window-ii/</guid>
      <description>This article is continuation of the previous article about sliding windows I which talks about fixed length sliding window. In this aritcle will look for problems which can be solved using variable length sliding window. Variable length sliding window problems are more tricky to detect. Sometimes a problem will mention a window which makes it easier, but sometimes that conclusion needs to be done by analyzing and running examples in the problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting N numbers</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sorting-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 23:26:04 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sorting-all/</guid>
      <description>In this article will be adding different ways to sort an array of n numbers and code snippets for each one of them. Idea with this post is to keep all the sorting methods with code snippets in one place, for comparison purpose.
Leetcode problem:
 Sort an array  Decease &amp;amp; Conqure Strategies: Bubble Sort  Time Complexity: O(N^2) In Place Stable  def sortArray(nums: List[int]) -&amp;gt; List[int]: # Bubble sort: Top down strategy, first do work then delegate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sliding window I</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sliding-window/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 18:34:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/sliding-window/</guid>
      <description>In arrays and strings, there are a subset of problems which deal with window of subarrays or substrings. In such problems the idea is to search a subarray matching a particular condition. A brute-force way of checking all the sub-arrays or substrings gives a runtime complexity of O(N^2). Sliding Window technique can be really helpful in such problems to reduce the time complexity to O(N) in such problems. In this post I would be discussing some common code templates which can be used for solving using sliding window techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Permutations I</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 16:36:17 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/permutations/</guid>
      <description>Finding permutations of elements in an array, is a fairly simple problem with the usage of recursion and backtracking.
In this article, adding a template to help with these kind of problems.
Example Problems:
 Permutations Permutations II  In the two problems the only difference is that in one problem all the numbers are unique and in other it is not. If all the numbers are not unique in the array then the number of permutations decreases by a factor of similar numbers factorial i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monotonic Data Structures</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/monotonic-stack/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 10:53:20 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/monotonic-stack/</guid>
      <description>Stacks are quite simple data structures with LIFO (Last In First Out) property. I added this post with the implementation of a stack using list/slice in python and go.
More constraint properties can be added to this simple stack structure, which can help solve multiple other problems.
In this post I will be talking about stack with monotonic property.
Monotone means same or unchanging. Defining stacks with monotonic increasing/decreasing properties means all elements in the stack are unchangingly increasing or decreasing in nature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stacks in go and python</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/stacks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 19:21:55 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/stacks/</guid>
      <description>Using list as a stack in python Stacks come very handy in solving some of the problems. Often using just an array does the purpose rather than specific data structures.
In python to use a list as a stack is straight forward with append and pop methods already available.
if __name__ == &#39;__main__&#39;: st = [] for i in range(10): st.append(i) for i in range(10): top = st.pop() print(top)  Using slices as a stack in go In go to use slices as a stack, push and pop methods are missing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partitioning an Array</title>
      <link>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/array-partition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 19:23:29 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adityabhatia.com/algos-ds/array-partition/</guid>
      <description>Paritioning an array is a common problem in computer science. In quick sort, the array is partitioned into smaller/equal and larger values based on the pivot. There are many other partition problems, where partition function is slightly different than the one in quick sort. Along with partitioning array the same partitioning technique can be used to find kth smallest/largest element in the array using quick select.
In this post describing a generic code template based on the Nico Lomuto algorithm to solve such partition problems in O(n) time and O(1) space.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>